Today's computers are so amazing
حواسيب اليوم مذهلة جداً
that we fail to notice how terrible they really are.
لدرجة أننا نفشل في ملاحظة كم هي سيئة.
I'd like to talk to you today about this problem,
أود أن أحدثكم اليوم عن هذه المشكلة،
and how we can fix it with neuroscience.
وكيف يمكننا إصلاحها بعلم الأعصاب.
First, I'd like to take you back to a frosty night in Harlem in 2011
أود أولاً العودة بكم إلى ليلة باردة في حي (هارلم) عام 2011
that had a profound impact on me.
كان لها تأثير عميق علي.
I was sitting in a dive bar outside of Columbia University,
كنت جالسا في حانة محلية خارج جامعة كولوميبا.
where I studied computer science and neuroscience,
حيث درست علوم الحاسوب و علم الأعصاب،
and I was having this great conversation with a fellow student
كنت مع أحد الزملاء الطلبة في خضم محادثة شيقة
about the power of holograms to one day replace computers.
عن قدرة الصّور المجسّمة على استبدال الحواسيب يوما ما.
And just as we were getting to the best part of the conversation,
و بينما كنا سنصل إلى الجزء الأكثر تشويقا من الحديث،
of course, his phone lights up.
أضاء هاثفه بالطبع.
And he pulls it towards himself, and he looks down and he starts typing.
سحبه باتجاهه و نظر إليه و بدأ بالطباعة.
And then he forces his eyeballs back up to mine and he goes,
ثم بدأ بإجبار عينيه على النظر إلي و هو يقول،
"Keep going. I'm with you."
"أكمل لك كامل تركيزي."
But of course his eyes were glazed over,
لكن بالطبع كانت عيناه ملتصقتان بالهاثف،
and the moment was dead.
و ماتت اللحظة.
Meanwhile across the bar,
في الجانب الآخر من الحانة
I noticed another student holding his phone,
لاحظت طالبا آخر يحمل هاتفه.
this time towards a group.
هذه المرة كان مع مجموعة.
He was swiping through pictures on Instagram,
كان يتصفح الصور على إنستغرام،
and these kids were laughing hysterically.
و كان أولئك الأولاد يضحكون بشكل هيستيري.
And that dichotomy between how crappy I was feeling
و هذه الإزدواجية بين شعوري المزري
and how happy they were feeling about the same technology,
و شعورهم بالسعادة حول نفس التكنولوجيا.
really got me thinking.
دفعتني للتفكير.
And the more I thought of it, the more I realized
و كلما تمعنت في الأمر إلا و أدركت
it was clearly not the digital information that was the bad guy here,
أن العامل السلبي في المعادلة لم يكن المعلومات الرقمية،
it was simply the display position that was separating me from my friend
بل كان ببساطة موضع الشاشة التي كانت تفصلني عن صديقي
and that was binding those kids together.
و كانت تجمع ما بين أولئك الأولاد.
See, they were connected around something,
كما ترون، فقد كانوا مجتمعين حول شيءٍ ما،
just like our ancestors who evolved their social cognitions
تماما مثل أسلافنا الذين طوروا استعرافهم الإجتماعي
telling stories around the campfire.
يروون القصص حول نار المخيم.
And that's exactly what tools should do, I think.
و هذا بالضبط دور الأدوات، على ما أظن.
They should extend our bodies.
دورها يكمن في مد قدرات أجسامنا.
And I think computers today are doing quite the opposite.
و أظن أن الحواسيب اليوم تقوم بعكس ذلك.
Whether you're sending an email to your wife
سواء كنت ترسل بريداً إلكترونياً إلى زوجتك
or you're composing a symphony
أو كنت تؤلف معزوفة موسيقية
or just consoling a friend,
أو تواسي صديقا،
you're doing it in pretty much the same way.
فأنت تفعل كل ذلك بنفس الطريقة تقريبا.
You're hunched over these rectangles,
أنت تنحني فوق تلك المستطيلات،
fumbling with buttons and menus and more rectangles.
تضغط على الأزرار و القوائم و المزيد من المستطيلات.
And I think this is the wrong way,
و خطر لي أن هذه هي الطريقة الخطأ،
I think we can start using a much more natural machine.
أظن أننا نستطيع استعمال آلة أكثر قربا للطبيعة.
We should use machines that bring our work back into the world.
علينا استعمال آلات تعيد عملنا إلى أرض الواقع.
We should use machines that use the principles of neuroscience
علينا استعمال آلات تستعمل مبادئ علم الأعصاب
to extend our senses versus going against them.
لمد مدارك أحاسيسنا بدل تقليصها.
Now it just so happens that I have such a machine here.
شاءت الظروف أن تكون لدي مثل هذه الآلة معي.
It's called the Meta 2.
تسمى الميتا 2.
Let's try it out.
لنجربها.
Now in front of me right now, I can see the audience,
أرى الجمهور مباشرة أمامي،
and I can see my very hands.
و أرى يداي.
And in three, two, one,
و خلال ثلاثة، إثنان، واحد،
we're going to see an immersive hologram appear,
سوف نرى صورة طيفية،
a very realistic hologram appear in front of me,
صورة طيفية في غاية الواقعية تظهر أمامي،
of our very glasses I'm wearing on my head right now.
أمام نظارتي هاته التي أرتديها الآن.
And of course this could be anything that we're shopping for
و يمكن أن يكون هذا أي شيءنتسوق لأجله
or learning from,
أو نتعلم منه،
and I can use my hands
و أستطيع استعمال يداي
to very nicely kind of move it around with fine control.
و أحركها بكل سهولة.
And I think Iron Man would be proud.
وأعتقد أن الرجل الحديدي سيكون فخورا.
We're going to come back to this in just a bit.
سنعود لهذا خلال لحظات.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now if you're anything like me, your mind is already reeling
الآن، إذا كنتم مثلي فلابد و أن عقلكم مترنح
with the possibilities of what we can do with this kind of technology,
من إمكانيات ما ستسمح لنا هذه التكنولوجيا من فعله،
so let's look at a few.
لننظر لبعض منها.
My mom is an architect,
أمي مهندسة معمارية،
so naturally the first thing I imagined
إذا من الطبيعي أن أول ما تخيلته
was laying out a building in 3D space
كان بسط بناء في فضاء ثلاثي الأبعاد
instead of having to use these 2D floor plans.
بدل استعمال هذه المخططات ثنائية الأبعاد.
She's actually touching graphics right now
إنها تلمس الرسوم في هذه اللحظة
and selecting an interior decor.
و تختار ديكورا داخليا.
This was all shot through a GoPro through our very glasses.
تم تصوير كل هذا عبر كاميرا "غو برو" من خلال نظاراتنا الخاصة.
And this next use case is very personal to me,
هذا الإستعمال الثاني له خصوصية عندي،
it's Professor Adam Gazzaley's glass brain project,
إنه مشروع البروفيسور (آدام غازالي) تمثيل الدماغ الزجاجي،
courtesy of UCSF.
بفضل جامعة كاليفورنيا في سان فرانسيسكو.
As a neuroscience student,
بصفتي تلميذا في علم الأعصاب،
I would always fantasize
فأنا دائما أحلم
about the ability to learn and memorize these complex brain structures
بالقدرة على تعلم و حفظ كل هذه البنيات الدماغية المعقدة
with an actual machine,
بواسطة آلة حقيقية،
where I could touch and play with the various brain structures.
تمكنني من لمس و التلاعب بمختلف البنيات الدماغية.
Now what you're seeing is called augmented reality,
ما ترونه يسمى بالواقع المعزز،
but to me, it's part of a much more important story --
لكن بالنسبة لي الأمر مرتبط بقصة أكثر تعقيدا --
a story of how we can begin to extend our bodies with digital devices,
قصة كيف يمكننا مد قدرات جسدنا بواسطة الأجهزة الرقمية
instead of the other way around.
بدل القيام بالعكس.
Now ...
الآن...
in the next few years, humanity's going to go through a shift, I think.
أظن أنه في الأعوام القليلة القادمة، ستمر الإنسانية عبر تحول ما.
We're going to start putting an entire layer of digital information
سنبدأ بوضع طبقة كاملة من المعلومات الرقمية
on the real world.
على أرض الواقع.
Just imagine for a moment
تخيلوا لبرهة
what this could mean for storytellers,
ما قد يعنيه هذا للروائيين،
for painters,
و للرسامين،
for brain surgeons,
و جراحي الدماغ،
for interior decorators
و لمصممي الديكور الداخلي
and maybe for all of us here today.
و ربما لكل الحاضرين اليوم.
And what I think we need to do as a community,
و ما أظن أننا نحتاج فعله بصفتنا مجتمعا.
is really try and make an effort
هو المحاولة و القيام بمجهود
to imagine how we can create this new reality
لتخيل كيف يمكننا خلق هذا الواقع الجديد
in a way that extends the human experience,
بطريقة تمد من التجربة الإنسانية،
instead of gamifying our reality
بدل جعل واقعنا كلعبة
or cluttering it with digital information.
أو بعثرة المعلومات الرقمية فيه.
And that's what I'm very passionate about.
و هذا هو شغفي.
Now, I want to tell you a little secret.
أريد مشاركتكم بسر صغير.
In about five years --
بعد خمس سنوات --
this is not the smallest device --
هذا ليس أصغر الأجهزة --
in about five years,
بعد خمس سنوات تقريبا،
these are all going to look like strips of glass on our eyes
ستبدو كلها كأشرطة زجاجية على أعيننا
that project holograms.
تظهر الصور الطيفية.
And just like we don't care so much about which phone we buy
و كما لا نهتم بأي هاثف نشتري
in terms of the hardware -- we buy it for the operating system --
في ما يخص العتاديات -- نشتريه بسبب نظام النتشغيل --
as a neuroscientist,
بصفتي عالم أعصاب،
I always dreamt of building the iOS of the mind, if you will.
لطالما حلمت بعمل نظام تشغيل ذهني
And it's very, very important that we get this right,
و من المهم فعل ذلك بالطريقة الصحيحة،
because we might be living inside of these things
لأننا ربما عشنا داخل هذه الأشياء
for at least as long as we've lived
على الأقل طوال حياتنا
with the Windows graphical user interface.
بواسطة الواجهة الرسومية من ويندوز
And I don't know about you,
و لا أعلم بشأنكم،
but living inside of Windows scares me.
لكن العيش داخل نظام ويندوز يفزعني
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
To isolate the single most intuitive interface out of infinity,
لعزل الواجهة الأشهر عن اللانهاية،
we use neuroscience to drive our design guidelines,
نستعمل علم الأعصاب لتوجيه مبادئنا التصميمية
instead of letting a bunch of designers fight it out in the boardroom.
بدل ترك مجموعة من المصممين يتقاتلون حولها في حجرة الاجتماعات.
And the principle we all revolve around
و المبدأ الذي نصبو إليه جميعا
is what's called the "Neural Path of Least Resistance."
يسمى بـ "المسار العصبي الأقل مقاومة."
At every turn, we're connecting the iOS of the brain with our brain
في كل منعطف، نصل بين نظام التشغيل الذهني مع عقلنا
on, for the first time, our brain's terms.
لأول مرة بخصوصيات أدمغتنا.
In other words, we're trying to create a zero learning-curve computer.
بمعنى أننا نحاول صنع حاسوبا سهل الإستخدام.
We're building a system that you've always known how to use.
نبني نظاما لطالما عرفتم كيفية استعماله.
Here are the first three design guidelines that we employ
هذه هي المبادئ التصميمية الثلاثة الأولى التي نوظفها
in this brand-new form of user experience.
في تجربة المستخدم الجديدة هذه.
First and foremost, you are the operating system.
المبدأ الأول و الأهم هو أنتم هم نظام التشغيل.
Traditional file systems are complex and abstract,
أنظمة الملفات التقليدية معقدة و مجردة.
and they take your brain extra steps to decode them.
و تتطلب من دماغكم جهدا أكبر لفك شيفرتها.
We're going against the Neural Path of Least Resistance.
و تعمل ضد المسار العصبي الأقل مقاومة.
Meanwhile, in augmented reality,
بينما في الواقع المعزز
you can of course place your holographic TED panel over here,
تستطيعون بالطبع وضع الصورة الطيفية لمنصة TED هنا،
and your holographic email on the other side of the desk,
و الصورة الطيفية لبريدكم الإلكتروني على هذا الجانب من المكتب،
and your spatial memory evolved just fine to go ahead and retrieve them.
و قد تطورت ذاكرتكم الموضعية بشكل يسمح بإيجادها.
You could put your holographic Tesla that you're shopping for --
تستطيعون وضع مجسم سيارة "تيسلا" الذي تودون شراءه --
or whatever model my legal team told me to put in right before the show.
أو مهما كان الذي طلب مني فريقي القانوني وضعه قبل العرض.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Perfect. And your brain knows exactly how to get it back.
عظيم، دماغكم يعرف بالضبط كيف يسترجعه.
The second interface guideline we call "touch to see."
المبدأ الثاني نسميه بـ "اللمس للرؤية".
What do babies do when they see something that grabs their interest?
ما الذي يفعله الأطفال حين يرون شيئا يثير انتباههم؟
They try and reach out and touch it.
يحاولون الوصول إليه و لمسه.
And that's exactly how the natural machine should work as well.
و هذا بالضبط كيف يجب أن تعمل الآلة الطبيعية.
Turns out the visual system gets a fundamental boost
تبين أن النظام المرئي يحصل على دفعة أساسية
from a sense we call proprioception --
من حاسة نسميها استقبال الحس العميق--
that's the sense of our body parts in space.
إنها حاسة إدراك الأعضاء الداخلية.
So by touching our work directly, we're not only going to control it better,
إذن عبر لمس عملنا مباشرة، لن نتمكن فقط من التحكم فيه بشكل أفضل،
we're also going to understand it much more deeply.
بل سنفهمه أيضا بشكل أعمق.
Hence, touch to see.
و منه أتت فكرة "اللمس للرؤية".
But it's not enough to experience things ourselves.
لكنها غير كافية لتجربة الأشياء بأنفسنا.
We're inherently these social primates.
فنحن من الرئيسيات الإجتماعية.
And this leads me to our third guideline,
ما يقودني إلى المبدإ الثالث،
the holographic campfire from our first story.
نار المخيم المجسمة من قصتنا الأولى.
Our mirror-neuron subsystem suggests
تشير خلية العصبونات المرآتية خاصتنا
that we can connect with each other and with our work much better
إلى أنه بإمكاننا التواصل بشكل أفضل مع بعضنا البعض و مع عملنا
if we can see each other's faces and hands in 3D.
إذا استطعنا رؤية وجوه وأيدي بعضنا بشكل ثلاثي الأبعاد.
So if you look at the video behind me,
إذا نظرتم إلى الفيديو ورائي،
you can see two Meta users playing around with the same hologram,
ترون مستخدمي جهاز ميتا يلعبان بنفس الصورة الطيفية،
making eye contact, connected around this thing,
يتواصلان بالأعين، و متصلان حول هذا الشيء،
instead of being distracted by external devices.
بدل أن يتشتت انتباههما بالأجهزة الخارجية.
Let's go ahead and try this again with neuroscience in mind.
لنجرب هذا ثانية مع أخد علم الأعصاب بالإعتبار.
So again, our favorite interface, the iOS of the mind.
إذن، نظامنا التشغيلي المفضل، نظام التشغيل الذهني.
I'm going to now take a step further
سأتقدم الآن خطوة إلى الأمام
and go ahead and grab this pair of glasses
و آخد هذه النظارة
and leave it right here by the desk.
و أتركها هنا بجانب المكتب.
I'm now with you, I'm in the moment,
أنا حاضر معكم في هذه اللحظة،
we're connecting.
نحن في اتصال.
My spatial memory kicks in, and I can go ahead and grab it
تفعل ذاكرتي الموضعية و أستطيع أخذها
and bring it right back here, reminding me
و جلبها نحوي،فتذكرني
that I am the operating system.
أنني أنا نظام التشغبل.
And now my proprioception is working,
و حاسة استقبال الحس العميق لدي تعمل،
and I can go ahead and explode these glasses into a thousand parts
و أستطيع تفجير هذه النظارات إلى ملايين القطع
and touch the very sensor that is currently scanning my hand.
و ألمس المجس الذي يمسح بصمة يدي الآن.
But it's not enough to see things alone,
لكن رؤية الأشياء وحيدها غير كافية،
so in a second, my co-founder Ray is going to make a 3D call --
بعد ثانية سيقوم شريكي (راي) بمكالمة ثلاثية الأبعاد --
Ray?
(راي)؟
(Ringing)
(رنين الهاثف)
Hey Ray, how's it going?
(راي) كيف الأحوال؟
Guys, I can see this guy in front me in full 3D.
أستطيع رؤيته أمامي بشكل ثلاثي الأبعاد.
And he is photo-realistic.
و هو في غاية الواقعية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
My mirror-neuron subsystem suggests that this is going to replace phones
هذا سيستبدل الهواثف بحسب خلية العصبونات المرآتية
in not too long.
في المستقبل غير البعيد.
Ray, how's it going?
(راي) كيف هي الأحوال؟
Ray: Great. We're live today.
(راي): عظيم نحن على المباشر.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
MG: Ray, give the crowd a gift
(ميرون غريبيتز): (راي)، أعطي الجمهور هدية
of the holographic brain we saw from the video earlier.
الدماغ الطيفي الذي رأيناه في الفيديو آنفا.
Guys, this is not only going to change phones,
هذا لن يغير الهواثف فقط،
it's also going to change the way we collaborate.
بل أيضا الطريقة التي نتعاون بها.
Thank you so much.
شكرا جزيلا لك.
Thanks, Ray.
شكرا لك (راي).
Ray: You're welcome.
(راي): على الرحب و السعة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
MG: So folks, this is the message that I discovered in that bar in 2011:
(ميرون غريبيتز): هذه هي الرسالة التي اكتشفت في تلك الحانة في 2011.
The future of computers is not locked inside one of these screens.
مستقبل الحواسيب ليس موجودا في أحد هذه الشاشات.
It's right here, inside of us.
إنه هنا، بداخلنا جميعا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So if there's one idea that I could leave you with here today,
إذا كانت هناك فكرة واحدة أريد طرحها لكم،
it's that the natural machine is not some figment of the future,
فهي أن الآلة الطبيعية ليست خيالا من المستقبل،
it's right here in 2016.
بل هي هنا في 2016.
Which is why all hundred of us at Meta,
لهذا جميع الأشخاص المئة في شركة ميتا،
including the administrative staff,
بما فيهم فريق الإدارة،
the executives,
المدراء التنفيذيون،
the designers, the engineers --
و المصممون و المهندسون --
before TED2017,
و قبل مؤتمر TED2017،
we're all going to be throwing away our external monitors
سنرمي شاشات حواسيبنا
and replacing them with a truly and profoundly more natural machine.
و نستبدلها بآلة طبيعية بحق.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you, appreciate it.
شكرا لكم، أقدر ذلك.
Thanks, guys.
شكرا جميعا.
Chris Anderson: So help me out on one thing,
(كريس أندرسون): أطلعني على شيء واحد.
because there've been a few augmented reality demos
لأنه قدمت القليل من العروض التوضيحية عن الواقع المعزز
shown over the last year or so out there.
على مدار السنة الماضية تقريبا.
And there's sometimes a debate among technologists
و هناك سجال بين الخبراء التكنولوجيين.
about, are we really seeing the real thing on-screen?
موضوعه هل نحن فعلا نرى شيئا حقيقيا على الشاشة؟
There's this issue of field of view,
هناك مسألة متعلقة بمجال الرؤية،
that somehow the technology is showing a broader view
بطرقة ما ترينا التكنولوجيا رؤية أوسع
than you would actually see wearing the glasses.
مما يمكن أن تراه عبر النظارة.
Were we seeing the real deal there?
هل ما رأيناه كان حقيقيا؟
MG: Absolutely the real deal.
(ميرون غريبيتز): بالتأكيد.
Not only that,
ليس هذا فحسب،
we took extra measures to shoot it with a GoPro through the actual lens
بل أخدنا احتياطات إضافية لتصويره عبر العدسات بكاميرا "غو برو"
in the various videos that you've seen here.
في مختلف اللقطات التي شاهدناها.
We want to try to simulate the experience for the world
نريد محاكاة التجربة الواقعية
that we're actually seeing through the glasses,
التي نراها عبر النظارة،
and not cut any corners.
بدون أي خدع.
CA: Thank you so much for showing us that.
(كريس أندرسون): شكرا لأنك أريتنا ذلك. (ميرون غريبيتز): أقدر ذلك، شكرا جزيلا